<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on SIMONA SIMONA</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on SIMONA SIMONA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 21:13:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Research Software and Statistical Programming to Social Science Students: A note to Instructors</title>
      <link>/post/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Introduction
Statistical programming and sofware more generally has become ubiquitous in the social sciences. I think it is fare to say that almost all social science students today will face the need to learn some kind of software at one or two points in their learning journey. The need for software and programming skills in our society has exponentiated in the past decade due to an avalance data availability. The so called big data revolution is taking the world by storm and the social sciences will not be spared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter Data Mining</title>
      <link>/post/twitter_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/twitter_data/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I document the process and tools used to acquire data from the Twitter API. I will use the R statistical programming language through RStudio in this process. It is important that you install R and RStudio on your machine, including all the accompanying packages specified here. Get documentation providing installation guides for both R and RStudio here. We are going to use the RStudio environment for our data collection but of course it will not work properly if you haven’t installed R first as he installation document explains.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a website with Blogdown and R Markdown</title>
      <link>/post/creating-website/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/creating-website/</guid>
      <description>Building a website It is always a good idea to spread the good news when you come across a fantastic resource to help others and also to give credit to those who have invested enormous amount of time and energy developing it. I made this website in RStudio, an open-source integrated development environment for R, using the blogdown package. I am still rusty in html, CSS and JavaScript, which are the languages commonly used to build websites ground-up.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>